NAVEEN N RAVICHANDRASEKARAN

250 East 6th Street, Apt 0402 \$\infty\$ Saint Paul, MN 55101

(832) · 720 · 2393 ♦ http://www.naveenravichandrasekaran.com/ ♦ nravi.research@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Professional Software Engineer with experience in the general areas of parallel and distributed computing. Specifically, my technical skills focus on the following areas: (i) parallel programming models and runtime systems (MPI and Partitioned Global Address Space models like OpenSHMEM, Global Arrays, and Coarray Fortran); (ii) parallel computing architectures (Cray Supercomputers and Clusters, multi-core systems, GPUs and Intel MIC), and (iii) high-speed interconnect libraries(DMAPP)

EDUCATION

University of Houston, Main Campus

December 2015

M.S. in Computer Science - Specialization in Parallel & Distributed Systems

Anna University, India

May 2011

Bachelors in Engineering - Electrical & Electronics Engineering

EXPERIENCE

Cray, Inc

12/26/2015 - Present

Software Engineer - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul, MN

- · HPC and parallel programming runtime optimizations for Cray supercomputer and cluster hardware to be utilized by specific customers like U.S government and commercial petroleum industries
- · Work specifically on Cray software stacks like Cray MPICH, Cray SHMEM, and Global Arrays
- · Participate and represent Cray in OpenSHMEM standards committee

Cray, Inc

05/18/2015 - 12/25/2015

Intern - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul, MN

- · Research, Prototype, and Implement new features in Cray SHMEM programming library
- · Optimize Global Arrays library for NAMD and NWChem Chemistry applications

University of Houston

09/14/2013 - 05/15/2015

Research Assistant - HPC Tools

Houston, TX

- · Research Assistant to Dr.Barbara Chapman(Chair, Computer Science & Mathematics(CSM) Group Brookhaven National Laboratory)
- · Research and explore strategies for runtime optimizations, and compiler-tools interactions for large-scale parallel systems using OpenSHMEM and Coarray Fortran programming models

Cognizant Technology Solutions

06/23/2011 - 07/12/2013

Programmer Analyst

Chennai, India

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Computer Languages

C/C++, Fortran, Python

Parallel Programming Models

OpenSHMEM, MPI, Coarray Fortran, OpenMP

Network Libraries

DMAPP, Verbs, Libfabrics

Architectures

Cray Supercomputers, & Clusters, Intel MIC

PROJECTS

Current Projects

1. Cray OpenSHMEMX

- Cray OpenSHMEMX is a new SHMEM library implementation developed to supersede the existing production ready Cray SHMEM library on future exascale Cray architectures
- Design and develop Cray OpenSHMEMX from scratch with support for different transport layers including DMAPP, XPMEM, and Libfabrics
- Provide complete backward compatibility with Cray SHMEM with all Cray specific features

2. Cray MPICH

• create an optimized message matching layer for the MPI implementation.

Past Projects

- 1. Cray SHMEM Project description: Cray SHMEM is a production quality SHMEM implementation for different Cray platforms with OpenSHMEM standards compliant. My Contributions: I am particularly involved in maintaining library along with implementing new features as per the OpenSHMEM standards, also propose and prototype new features like Communication Contexts, Symmetric Memory Partitions and Teams(PE-Subsets).
- 2. Cray Global Arrays(Cray-GA) ComEx-DMAPP Project description: Global Arrays is a PGAS library from Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL). My Contributions: I was involved in optimizing and maintain the ComEx DMAPP communication layer.

3. OpenSHMEM Reference Implementation

Project description: University of Houston worked with *Oak Ridge National Laboratory* to standardize OpenSHMEM via a community-driven specification with a reference implementation. **My Contributions:** I have been particularly involved in the optimization of the collective communication performance.

4. Coarray Fortran

Project description: Coarray Fortran is a set of new language features incorporated into the Fortran 2008 standard to enable parallel programming in Fortran with minimal changes to the language syntax. It is a joint project between University of Houston and *Total* **My Contributions:** I was particularly involved in the optimization of the Coarray Fortran runtime library with new underlying communication layers.

KEY ACTIVITIES

1. OpenSHMEM standardization Effort, Participate and represent Cray Inc. in OpenSHMEM standards committee. http://openshmem.org/

AWARDS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- 1. Best Paper Award, 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Model(PGAS 2014).
- 2. Graduate Assistant Tution Fellowship, September 2013 May 2015.
- 3. Best Undergraduate Student Project, Mepco Schlenk Engineering College, Anna University, India, 2011.

REFEREED CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

My full name is **Naveen Namashivayam Ravichandrasekaran** and I author all conference and workshop publications as **Naveen Namashivayam**.

- 1. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, D.Pou, and M.Pagel. "Introducing Cray OpenSHMEMX A Modular Multi-Communication Layer OpenSHMEM Implementation.". In Proceedings of Fifth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies, August, 2017, Hanover, Maryland, USA.
- 2. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, K.Kandalla, D.Pou, J.Robichaux, J.Dinan, and M.Pagel. "Symmetric Memory Partitions in OpenSHMEM: A case study with Intel KNL". In Proceedings of Fourth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Big Compute and Big Data Convergence, August, 2017, Annapolis, Maryland, USA. https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-73814-7_1
- 3. K.Kandalla, P.Mendygral, N.Radcliffe, B.Cernohous, N.Namashivayam, K.McMahon, C.Sadlo and M.Pagel "Current State of the Cray MPT Software Stacks on the Cray XC Series Supercomputers". In proceedings of Cray User Group Meeting, 2017, Redmond, Washington, USA.
- 4. N.Namashivayam, D.Knaak, B.Cernohous, N.Radcliffe, and M.Pagel. "An Evaluation of Thread-Safe and Contexts-Domains Features in Cray SHMEM". In Proceedings of Third Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Enhancing OpenSHMEM for Hybrid Environments, August, 2016, Hanover, Maryland, USA. https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-50995-2_11
- N.Namashivayam, D.Eachempati, D.Khaldi and B.Chapman. "OpenSHMEM as a Portable Communication Layer for PGAS Models A Case Study with Coarray Fortran". In Proceedings of IEEE Cluster 2015, September, 2015, Chicago, USA.
 https://www.computer.org/csdl/proceedings/cluster/2015/6598/00/6598a438.pdf
- 6. N.Namashivayam, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati and B.Chapman. "Extending the Strided Communication Interface in OpenSHMEM". In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, Maryland, USA. https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-26428-8_1
- 7. D.Knaak, and N.Namashivayam. "Proposing OpenSHMEM Extensions Towards a Future for Hybrid Programming and Heterogeneous Computing", In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, Maryland, USA. https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2952638
- 8. N.Namashivayam, S.Ghosh, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati, and B.Chapman. "Native Mode-Based Optimizations of Remote Memory Accesses in OpenSHMEM for Intel Xeon Phi", 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Models (PGAS 2014). https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2676881

THESIS

• N.Namashivayam. "OpenSHMEM as an Effective Communication Layer for PGAS Models". Master's Thesis, University of Houston, October, 2015. https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/1c6b/9787b0eda7723a14ba6bc92cd77a7dcb0102.pdf